<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-26T21:02:07+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Michaldeutsch</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2026/michaldeutsch/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Michaldeutsch"/><published>2026-01-25T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-25T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2026/michaldeutsch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2026/michaldeutsch/"><![CDATA[<p>Hello everyone,</p> <p>today is Monday, I was enjoying the weekend, so had no time to write a blog. Sidenote: last two weeks I was working on my ‘Bookshelf’ and ‘Projects’ folder, rather than this blog. Sorry for this ;)</p> <p>What? Michal enjoying the weekend? Yeah, so it happens, I am slowed down a bit this semester, and even though it is exam season I am trying not be completely die and have a life in between a little bit. Strange, also getting used to it. At the same time I am kinda worried that I have underestimated the exam, so the last few days will be intense that is for sure.</p> <p>The story that I wanted to tell today comes from Saturday. My lovely friend Max and I we were practicing our Swiss German together. It is our shared hobby, and as neither of us is Swiss we at least have the courage to speak with one another, and that is good. I try my best to consume as much content as possible, but poor Max, poor Max, he only learns from me. And we were in a supermarket, and a friend of mine (who is Swiss) heard Max talking in Swiss German. And he thought: “That sounds like Michal.” That is weird. So he went to investigate and indeed, not too far he also found me!</p> <p>I laugh my ass off telling this story. The thing is, I also picked up my accent from Loris Zimmerli, a swiss influencer. And he (on purpuse) speaks in a very funny accent, so that he can entertain people. So that is how Michal German, oder Michaldeutsch came to be. Learn it, it is very funny!</p> <p>Have a nice day! Keep doing what you are doing, you do it great!</p> <p>Michal</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When you (accidently) start your own dialect.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New year!</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2026/new-year/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New year!"/><published>2026-01-03T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-03T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2026/new-year</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2026/new-year/"><![CDATA[<p>The new year is starting and I am still thinking about what I want 2026 to be like and what I can do about it: I do not know much yet, but there is a couple things to focus on and to finish (especially related to my studies), and I set some resolutions too. But maybe that is not a smart way to think abou, I want to be more open about what the life can bring and embrace that, so I will just try to keep my eyes and options open :)</p> <p>Today in the morning I was woke up thinking about the verb “to download”, so I wanted to share that. While in Dutch and German this word is more or less directly translated: “downloaden” and “herunterladen”. In Czech, we use “stahovat” which would more literaly translate to “pull down”. The French the word is “télécharger”, where “charger” also means to “charge”, like to “charge a phone”, where “télé” would refer to being done from a distance. Similarly in Spanish, where the verb “descargar” would mean be closer to the meaning of “charge”, but the prefix “des” would indicate more like undoing something. It is interesting, because it made me think about how we adapt technology and what words we use for it. Few decades ago, there was no downloading of files, cause there was no (widely available) internet.</p> <p>I guess at this point in time I lack a conclusion on this thought, but I still thought I would share it. I guess same goes for 2026: no clue where it will lead me, but I am ready to share it too!</p> <p>Happy new year! Best of luck with all that you will do :)</p> <p>Michal</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What will it bring?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vánoce Vánoce přicházejí!</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/vanoce-prichazeji/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vánoce Vánoce přicházejí!"/><published>2025-12-13T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-13T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/vanoce-prichazeji</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/vanoce-prichazeji/"><![CDATA[<p>Ho ho ho, it is Sunday, and you already know what it means: time for my weekly therapy. I write my blog and empty here my thoughts about what is bothering me. I write this in VSCode, which is where I spend most of my time anyway these days, so it kind of feels like I am productive anyway.</p> <p>I wrote the title of the blog in Czech, but just because I felt like it. This is how I roll these days with languages—I just use the words that come first. For example, I cannot call the chopped tomatoes I get in the supermarket anything else than “tomatoblokjes,” because that is how they call them in the Netherlands. There are a couple of words in my vocabulary that are German. And Christmas will always be Vánoce, because that is how it has always been back at home.</p> <p>Yes, home! It is the time of the year when I get to go back there. Since 2021, I have joined this special club called “the expats.” How do you spot one? They are flying back home for Christmas, and all their friends do too. Some people from further away stay behind, but in the expat community this will never feel like home one can come back to.</p> <p>I was usually never eager to go back home. But coming back to Czechia lately, I have realized how much I have missed from the lives of other people that I left behind. I was silently just typing my blog from afar, but I have done too little visiting and have been visited way too little. Creating this blog has been therapy for that, for sure, but I am trying to catch up more. I book tickets for someone’s birthday, making sure that I see my family when I am back. I love what I do, but I was surely isolating myself from others and overweighting work too much. I want to be included in the lives of people around me, and for that I have to be there physically. Christmas is just the time for that. I am taking some time off in Czechia before returning to the pits of despair before exams.</p> <p>That is the plan, and I am looking forward.</p> <p>See you all soon, and if not, then after New Year’s. Merry Christmas!</p> <p>Michal</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Time to go home.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jungfraujoch</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/jungfraujoch/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jungfraujoch"/><published>2025-12-06T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-12-06T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/jungfraujoch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/jungfraujoch/"><![CDATA[<p>Sunday it is again!</p> <p>It is also the time of the year now: Christmas are just around the corner! This means the semester is ending, I have to plan my travels home and try get some gifts for the my dear ones. Fitting this all together with all deadlines and social events seems to be impossible. My now it seems like I have succesfully mastered the craft of constantly losing my mind in situations like this, I take a deep breath, ask the good lord for some peace in my soul and go on. Today I thought I would not let my thoughts drown me and I would still go and write my blog.</p> <p>I have a nice thing to share, this semester I have taken the Applied Glaciology course, where I learned a lot about how glaciers do what they do. They actually do quite a lot of things, on top of the mountain the temperatures are low so the precipitation solidifies into new ice. At the bottom of the glacier the temperatures are usually high, this means that the glacier is melting. The most interesting thing in my opinion happens in between, the glacier is moving! Ice is not fixed, through the pressure created by itself pushing from the top it moves down the mountain! I recommend watching videos like <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TWGR6FxFlt8">this one</a> to get the feelings of what is happening.</p> <p>As a part of this course, we have gone up to Jungfraujoch for an excursion. On the way there, we have seen a small avalanche from a glacier that has torn off!</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-avalanche-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-avalanche-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-avalanche-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-avalanche.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500" height="300" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>On the top we have enjoyed the views, and relaxed for a bit!</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-group-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-group-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-group-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-group.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500" height="300" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>And we fed the birds that go all the way up there, just to be fed by the tourists.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-birds-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-birds-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-birds-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/jungfraujoch-birds.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500" height="300" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>It was quite impressive to be up in 3500+ meters. It is actually quite tough to be up there. Especially climbing stairs is tough, as there is so little oxygen.</p> <p>So yeah, that was a little trip to break a bit out of the ordinary.</p> <p>Have a great week!</p> <p>PS: I set up Google Analytics now, so I can see once again stats about who is reading this :3</p> <p>Michal</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Just another week in Switzerland.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dreamland</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/dreamland/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dreamland"/><published>2025-11-15T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-15T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/dreamland</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/dreamland/"><![CDATA[<p>Beautiful Sunday morning,</p> <p>I hope you have slept well. It is the time of the week when the church bells go crazy in stark contrast to the empty and quiet streets. I decided to start writing my blog in English this week, though I had sketched it out first in Czech, because I thought I should make it more generally accessible. Now I know that Google Translate integration in browsers has my back, which is amazing because that means that this time I do not have to write with a specific audience in mind.</p> <p>I am slowly burning through the time given to me to complete the third semester of my master studies. It would not be the first time I am getting sentimental too early. I remember when I was about to graduate high school, I was contemplating since September the fact that one day I would not be doing my 8:00-15:00 at the same building as always. Sounded crazy to me. Though the life at uni is different, it seems that we have crossed the half-life of our cohort and that many people are already thinking of leaving.</p> <p>And that is great, but I have to admit that for me it is also hard. I find it hard to call a new place home, but it seems that as soon as I do it is time to move on. I remember saying goodbye to Groningen, but being ready to move on. But what I was kind of hoping is that the new destination could be home. What was also pulling me to Zurich was the upward mobility. And anybody who visits me here is stunned: in the heart of Europe, but still so much more rich than anywhere else. It is hard not to be charmed.</p> <p>But that absolutely means that a lot of people come here for the charm, make it a link in the chain of their career, rather than a part of their life. Same as in Groningen, the number of people who actually want to be integrated is quite low, and I have to say that makes me quite sad. Somehow relationships from the start seem somewhat shallow. That would totally be a fault of my own as well. Having a long-distance relationship, I do spend most of my evenings talking online on the phone, and when I get a long weekend off the last place where you can meet me before I fly off is the airport. So it absolutely goes both ways.</p> <p>What makes me sad is that this is not how I imagined my life. I hope that at one point I could find maybe a community of people, where I could stay and I could see a future in. It is only myself who I could blame for this emotion, but it seems that this is rather individual for everyone. If I want to fit in to the community that I am in right now, I should be jumping on the first opportunity of getting out of here to chase something else.</p> <p>I just realize that I have managed to leave Brno, and I have managed without thinking to leave Groningen. However, now I am thinking, where is the next place I will leave for? And why? What for?</p> <p>Lately, I have been listening to the song called <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=o_hXGZ8NXAA">Dreamland</a> by Fox Stevenson. It goes like this:</p> <blockquote> <p>Does everybody live in a dreamland?</p> <p>Is this dreamland all that we know?</p> <p>Swallowing us up in an avalanche and blurring these lines with smoke</p> </blockquote> <p>Maybe Zurich just as well could be the dreamland. Too good to be true. Everybody’s dream, but nobody’s true life.</p> <p>I always like to say that I turn dreams into reality, but maybe what is missing right now is the ability to turn reality into home. Maybe it has to do with how I would pride myself on achievements. Well, Fox Stevenson has it for me.</p> <blockquote> <p>They tell me that I should be a real man</p> <p>But my pride’ll be the first thing to go</p> <p>I gotta get out of this wasteland</p> <p>Cause this wasteland ain’t home</p> </blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Does everybody live in a dreamland?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nové životní problémy</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/job-market/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nové životní problémy"/><published>2025-11-08T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-08T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/job-market</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/job-market/"><![CDATA[<p>Je nedělní ráno v Curychu. To se pozná podle dvou věcí. Zaprvé je venku mrtvo, protože všechno je v neděli zavřené. Všichni vyspávají, nebo vaří nedělní obědy a chystají se do kostela. Za druhé, momentálně je 9:45, kostely zvoní o sto šest (teď jsem strávil 5 minut hledáním na internetu, co to znamená o sto šest, proč to říkáme; neví se to, ale zdá se, že se někdo vsadil, že někdo něco nezvládne za 106 dní, nebo to vzniklo z rčení “být s to”). Já jsem si včera hodil celý den volno, nic jsem nedělal, a tak se teď sbírám a řeším, co vlastně tento týden budu dělat a jak to budu dělat, hezky si to všechno plánuju. Součástí plánování je vyčistit si mozek od toho, co se událo, co mě trápí a co mi dělá radost, a tak píšu. Jak jsem někde slyšel (prý od Joan Didion): “Nevěděl jsem, co si myslím, než jsem to začal psát.”</p> <p>Zjistil jsem, že se mi v životě opakuje jeden takový vzorec, tak jsem se o tom chtěl zmínit. Já si totiž vždycky myslím, že až skončí jedna fáze, tak že už budu mít hotovo a nebudu se muset dál snažit. Uvažme tento příklad: Michálek, kterému bylo 16 let, byl na střední a pěkně ho štval dějepis. Ten si říkal: “Tak už jen teď zatnu zuby a za rok mám hotovo, a pak už se nikdy dějepis učit nebudu, budu mít čas dělat to, co mě zajímá.” No jo, pak jsem si řekl, tak jo, jdeme teda studovat umělou inteligenci, tak to už máme v názvu, že děláme to, co nás zajímá (reálně moje úvaha tehdy byla, že nemám čas dělat to, co mě zajímá, tak bych se tomu měl věnovat přímo a ne jít studovat třeba matematiku). No, tak prvák měl jako předměty lineární algebru a diferenciální počet, tak se ale musím věnovat těm – nemám čas zajímat se o to, co se opravdu děje v umělé inteligenci. Vždyť to studuju, tak se to snad dozvím, jednou mi to snad někdo řekne. Budu se tomu věnovat, až budu mít hotovo.</p> <p>Jak sami asi vidíte, tento přístup má několik problémů.</p> <ol> <li>Realita, že na nic nemám čas a musím se věnovat čistě povinnostem, není pravdivá. Zvlášť ne na střední škole. Povinnosti v tu chvíli jsou minimální, a když už v tu chvíli jsem cítil, že nemám mentální kapacitu ani číst knížky, co mě baví, protože beru svoje povinnosti moc vážně, tak bylo asi něco špatně.</li> <li>Oddaloval jsem věci, které mě opravdu zajímaly. Raději jsem se učil stupidní dějepis, než abych četl o tom, co mě opravdu zajímá. Neříkám, že dějepis nebyl nezajímavý, byl a je. Ale nikdy to nebylo to, co dávalo mému životu smysl. Místo toho, abych hledal co mě opravdu zajímá, jsem studoval věci, za které mě někdo odměnil dobrou známkou. Žádný člověk, o kterém někdo slyší, že se naučil sám programování, nebo někam posunul technologie (e.g. Daniel Ek ze Spotify), se neučil programování, protože ho za to někdo známkoval. Učil se ho proto, že to bylo to, co chtěl dělat, když měl volno.</li> <li>Reálně jsem si vždycky myslel, že radost je v tom, nic nemuset. Nemuset do školy, nemuset do práce, nemuset nikam. Když se mě někdo zeptal, když jsem byl malý, čím bych chtěl být, tak jsem říkal, že rentiérem. A pak jsem byl mega šťastný, když jsem našel práci jako plavčík, kde jsem prakticky celou dobu nemusel nic dělat. Reálně, co mi ale vždycky dávalo energii od života, bylo snažení. Snažení něčeho dosáhnout, ve studiích, v brigádách, ve sportu. Ten moment, kdy se člověk soustředí, zatne zuby a jde dál, byl vždycky super. Práce, kde nic dělat nemusím, je k ničemu. A tak dělat teď něco, abych později nemusel, nedává moc smysl, protože později nebudu mít co dělat.</li> </ol> <p>Proč to tak řeším teď? Tak se pomalu blížím ke konci studia, to tak vypadá. Jejda, sakra, a co dál?! Konec velkého snažení…! Nebo ne…? Čeká mě nesnesitelná lehkost bytí? Vidím, jak se ostatní okolo mě ženou za svou první pracovní pozicí. A já si říkám, co mě čeká tam? Další moment, kdy nebudu mít čas se nadechnout, protože se budu bát jen abych se dobře znal 20 stránek firemního dějepisu? Nebo snad možná nějaká nová lineární algebra, která mi zase nedá spát a já nebudu číst žádnou zajímavou knížku?</p> <p>A tak na chvíli odkládám učebnice, je přece víkend. Píšu si blog. Našel jsem novou knížku o tom, jak funguje mozek, která je velmi zajímavá. Učím se hrát kulečník. Snažím se reálně si všimnout lidí okolo sebe. Poznat je a zeptat se jich, jak se jim daří. Snažím se přemýšlet, co mě motivuje a co bych opravdu po zbytek života chtěl dělat. Možná z toho nebude maturitní průměr 1,0, možná z toho nebude 800 metrů za 2 minuty. Možná z toho nebude publikovaný článek. Ale možná to bude dávat smysl víc než jenom do té doby, než se to odevzdalo, odeběhlo a publikovalo. A možná z toho na konci dne zůstane víc než stopa strachu v duši z toho, že neudělám zkoušku. Možná čtení té knížky je to, co se počítá. Jakou knížku člověk četl, a jestli o ní přemýšlel. A ne to, že ji člověk dočetl, zapsal do čtenářského deníku a odevzdal ve čtvrtek ráno 9:35 do kabinetu češtináře. To je totiž nakonec úplně všem fuk.</p> <p>Tak jo, mějte se hezky. A dělejte to, co vám dává smysl.</p> <p>Michi (prý to je jedna švýcarská verze)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Jak jsem si myslel, že už mám pro jednou zase hotovo...]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Výlet do Mnichova</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/munich-trip/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Výlet do Mnichova"/><published>2025-11-01T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-11-01T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/munich-trip</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/munich-trip/"><![CDATA[<p>Dobrý den,</p> <p>je neděle ráno, já si sedím u svého laptopu, srkám čaj a přemýšlím, jak bude vypadat další týden. Hlavně je ale čas ohlédnout se za tím minulým. Nejdůležitějším zážitkem bylo, že jsem si na konci týdne vyrazil na výlet do Mnichova.</p> <p>Studuje tam bývalý spolužák z Groningenu, jmenuje se Sam. Kecali jsme o tom, jak se nám daří, o tom, jak jde život, zašli jsme do posilovny, Sam mi ukázal školu a centrum, a pak už jsem pádil zpět do Curychu.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/sam-tum-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/sam-tum-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/sam-tum-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/sam-tum.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500" height="300" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Bylo hezké vidět po dlouhé době někoho, kdo mě zná, jaký jsem byl dřív. Je to dobrá sebereflexe. A je taky fajn vidět město z pohledu někoho, kdo ho zná, bydlí tam a má s ním spojené příběhy.</p> <p>Takže asi tak. A jede se dál.</p> <p>Už se těším na Vánoce.</p> <p>Mějte se hezky.</p> <p>Michal</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Návštěva u bývalého spolužáka]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Polsko není tak daleko, jak by se člověku zdálo</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/polsko/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Polsko není tak daleko, jak by se člověku zdálo"/><published>2025-10-25T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-25T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/polsko</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/polsko/"><![CDATA[<p>Minulý týden jsem napsal blog, ale zapomněl jsem ho zveřejnit. Tak ho tu máte taky, ale s datem z minulosti. Je to trošku škoda, protože bych chtěl vysílat pravidelné signály o svém životě. Ale tak tento týden se toho tolik neudělo, a tak se necítím alespoň tak špatně, že jsem toho asi dnes tolik nenapíšu.</p> <p>Musím si se znova zmínit o tom, čeho jsem si už dříve všiml. Většinu času v zahraničí se snažím netrávit moc času s Čechy. Ne, že bych se jim vyhýbal, ale čistě to není mým cílem, snažím se raději trávit více času s lidmi jiných národností. No, a jak jste si možná všimli, často se tak stane, že mnoho z nich jsou Poláci.</p> <p>Včera jsem se náhodou v dostavil na jednu večerní polskou sešlost. Pilo se, tancovalo se, zpívalo se, a mluvilo se samozřejmě. Tak jsem si znova ověřil, že polštině se dá perfektně rozumět. A tak jsem si mluvil česky, oni polsky, a bylo nám fajn. A tak si říkám, že máme k Polsku mnohem blíž, než by si člověk na první pohled myslel. Vždycky jsme měl spojeno Česko a Slovensko, nikdy jsem sice sám v Českoslovenku nežil, ale historicky a kulturně mi to dávalo smysl. Ale Polsko pro mě bylo nějak dál. Naopak třeba Srbochorvatština spojuje národy přes hranice, i když je jiné spory rozdělily to různých států. Ale já k Polsku (možná si jen něco neuvědomuju) necítím žádný odpor, a tak se mi zdá, že ty rozdíly jsou menší, než všechno to, co máme společné.</p> <p>No takže tak.</p> <p>Tutaj wszystko jest dobre.</p> <p>Michal</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Kulturní schledání za hranicemi]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jürgen Schmidhuber v Curychu</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/jsh-has-lost-it/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jürgen Schmidhuber v Curychu"/><published>2025-10-21T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-21T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/jsh-has-lost-it</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/jsh-has-lost-it/"><![CDATA[<p>A jejda, je zase středa a já jsem zatím nevyprodukoval žádný blog. Minulý víkend jsem tu měl Uxue, bylo to moc fajn. Život se vyvíjí hodně rychle, ale 5 minut na blog bych si snad najít mohl.</p> <p>Chtěl bych tady do kamene vytesat svoje zklamání ze včerejší přednášky. Byl totiž v Curychu Jürgen Schmidhuber, jeden z nejslavnějších vědců v oboru umělé inteligence. Jeho <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=gLnCTgIAAAAJ&amp;hl=en&amp;oi=ao">Google Scholar profile</a> ukazuje, že má dohromady přes 300 000 citací. Největším jeho objevem jsou long-short term memory networks, neurální sítě na zpracování sekvenčních dat, které nezapomínají. Velká hvězda. A jak jsem psal minulý týden, AI mě stále zajímá. Musel jsem tam prostě být.</p> <p>No.</p> <p>Tak tedy velký pán přišel. A začal povídat, mával rukama (hodně, fakt hodně, on fakt rád mává rukama), a říkal slova, ale moc toho nebylo. Mluvil o evoluci, o robotice, o historii umělé inteligence, a všem možném i nemožném. O tom, co chybí, a o tom, co bylo.</p> <p>Jediné, co jsem si z toho ale odnesl je, že vidí umělou inteligenci, která se dnes používá podobně jako auta. Princip spalovacího motoru existuje už dlouho, ale stále se okolo něj inovuje, a proto máme dnes tak dobrá auta. On je jedním z lidí, kteří vymysleli “spalovací motor” dnešní umělé inteligence (principy, na kterých funguje). A podle něj posledních 10 let nevyprodukoval žádné nové opravdové inovace, a hlavní, co se řeší, je jak postavit okolo tohoto motoru to nejlepší auto.</p> <p>Za mě má pravdu, ale na druhou stranu nesleduje vůbec jaké nové trendy máme teď v umělé inteligenci. Podle mě nové spalovací motory inteligence právě vznikají, ale bez 20 let inženýrské práce okolo nich nebudeme vědět, že tyto motory k něčemu byly. Takže musíme trochu počkat teďka. A říkát, že se nic tak zásadního neděje, a že oni to už vymysleli všechni v 90. letech, mi přijde celkem smutné.</p> <p>No nic, jsem z toho trochu zklamaný. Ale což, jdu si hrát s umělou inteligencí.</p> <p>Mějte se krásně.</p> <p>Michal</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Další hvězda a inspirace.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Professional Impairment: Seeing Your Own Life Through the Lense of Artificial Intelligence</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/me-the-ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Professional Impairment: Seeing Your Own Life Through the Lense of Artificial Intelligence"/><published>2025-10-12T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-12T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/me-the-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/me-the-ai/"><![CDATA[<p>Although not a professional expert, it’s fair to say I’ve spent some time learning about AI. Honestly, it all started with YouTube binges; that’s when I realized I wanted to learn more about all of this and maybe even contribute. Then I happened to follow a bachelor’s degree in the area of Artificial Intelligence, and am now currently pursuing my Master’s, even though that goes more towards the mathematical theory and practical side of machine learning. Crazily enough, the hype around the area has only increased since the moment I started being interested in it. I’ve really had the wonderful luck of experiencing this growth first-hand. It is insane to see how much further we’ve moved in just a few years.</p> <p>Since I started to learn about AI in 2021/2022, I’ve been on a long journey. In some way I am much further, I’ve certainly learned a lot about programming, training models, and the intricacies of mathematics connected to all of it. However, in some way, I’m still the same. I still get my breath taken away by talks on this topic (my newest discovery being <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OD5UzhaDWfg">Blaise Aguera y Arcas</a>, I love listening to this guy). It’s still super exciting to read a good paper about a new concept or a view on AI (which there is at least one good one a day). Even more, I enjoy spending some time pondering where this technology will take us in the upcoming years, and how it will change our society. In those regards, I still feel like a curious little child.</p> <p>However, one might say that I sometimes push it too far, and nerd out too much. I love to talk about machine learning in my own life, and from time to time, I think about my life in terms of AI. It’s not a unique thing to project concepts from science to personal life, nor into your philosophical point of view on the world. I have a vague memory from undergrad where we learned about how with the development of computers scientists started to see humans as modular machines (CPU = processing of the brain, RAM = memory of the brain, etc.) (one can argue that this actually goes both ways and yes, that is true: computers were developed to mimic human capabilities, but still the point stands). In reverse, we like to project our human concepts onto machines, e.g., the current transformer architecture behind ChatGPT has something called an “attention”. What is more, all great scientists, like Turing or Einstein, seem to have philosophical depth to their findings, so maybe it’s all just a sign of greatness that I think about this.</p> <p>Either way, I wanted to share a few concepts of where I think machine learning meets my daily reality, and maybe some takeaways that one can derive from it. If you have never come across these technical terms, some (many) of the things will not make sense. I will try to explain everything from scratch as much as possible, but I already apologize if I didn’t succeed.</p> <h2 id="part-1-my-brain-is-a-neural-network">Part 1: My brain is a neural network.</h2> <p>Might seem obvious: our brains are in the end made of neurons, which is what has inspired the neural architectures. What is remarkable is to treat yourself as you would treat a neural network.</p> <ul> <li>Do you need to learn something? Supply yourself with as many input-output pairs as possible, and cycle through them many times.</li> <li>Are you mad at yourself that you forgot something? Don’t be. Learning a new thing means forgetting another one; in machine learning we call it <strong>‘catastrophic forgetting’</strong> and it happens all the time.</li> </ul> <p>That really aligns with how I see myself learning, but maybe I’m too influenced by what I study.</p> <h2 id="part-2-i-am-a-reinforcement-learning-agent">Part 2: I am a reinforcement learning agent.</h2> <p>We’ve seen AI lately get good at games like chess, or other interactive games. This area is called <strong>reinforcement learning</strong>, and it uses a reward signal to motivate agents to succeed in environments. Interestingly, humans are also such an agent! Our reward? <strong>Dopamine</strong>. We get rewarded when we feel successful, when we’ve done something right, and we don’t get any if we fail to complete our tasks.</p> <p>Closely connected to this is the notion of a <strong>discount</strong>: How much do you value a reward in the future as opposed to now? Are you willing to make a certain sacrifice to get more in the future and by how much? This is what discount controls. It is generally regarded that higher discount factors (meaning you sacrifice more for the future) are better for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stanford_marshmallow_experiment">success in life</a>.</p> <p>Finally, every agent finds itself in an environment that is unknown to it. It doesn’t know what actions lead to a better outcome, and which do not. Therefore it has to explore new actions. However, it doesn’t know if the actions it has already found are optimal; therefore it also needs to exploit the currently available options. This is known as the <strong>exploration / exploitation trade-off</strong>.</p> <h2 id="part-3-we-are-all-just-part-of-a-distribution">Part 3: We are all just part of a distribution.</h2> <p>Most people are average in most things, but exceptional in few. Some skills and abilities are correlated with others, while others are rather anti-correlated. And this reminds me of a randomly sampled vector from a Gaussian distribution. Everyone of us is basically sampled from a distribution of all people, and the role of learning about oneself is to apply <strong>principal component analysis</strong> to find out what components you are made of.</p> <p>One other place where I see distributions playing a huge role are opportunities in life. To find out what life is about, one should sample the distribution. Go out, and sample experiences, and try to find the place that feels the best.</p> <h2 id="part-4-life-is-an-optimization-process">Part 4: Life is an optimization process.</h2> <p>Lastly, when you set an AI model to run, you basically initiate a whole optimization process. And actually, the whole life sometimes feels like one big optimization process. As if everyone of us was actually an <strong>optimizer</strong>. We make steps in directions where we feel like we are going to do better.</p> <p>However, one should not make big steps (changing everything in one day) but rather work on making small steps in a direction. This is like <strong>gradient clipping</strong>, where one regulates the amount of change on each step to ensure stability of the learning process.</p> <p>Finally, I observed that actually one should change the learning rate, sometimes make a big change and then make more smaller changes later. That is exactly like the <strong>cosine scheduler</strong>, which helps modern models find the optima.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>If you made it here, you might be thinking: “Wow, Michal is really loosing it at this point.” Or maybe I’m just finding it; maybe I just internalized the concepts to the point where they are not leaving me for life. We will see whether that is a good or bad thing, but I hope these new paradigms of thinking about intelligence will push humanity further towards a better understanding of itself.</p> <p>I’m currently particularly excited about the movement sparked by Francois Chollet’s <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1911.01547">On the Measure of Intelligence</a>, which pushes AI researchers to consider new paradigms of intelligence. We already live in a world where computers can remember or look up better than we do.</p> <p>Keep in mind that the ideas that you hear here brought us computers that talk to us. This is insane.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learning about machine learning makes me learn about myself.]]></summary></entry></feed>