<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-22T18:44:33+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Domov číslo čtyři</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/novy-byt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Domov číslo čtyři"/><published>2025-09-22T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-22T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/novy-byt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/novy-byt/"><![CDATA[<p>Vítejte na novém blogu, minulý týden jsem ho dával dohromady, tak by teď měl nějak plus mínus obsahovat moje příspěvky, kterými bych se chtěl prezentovat.</p> <p>Jo, a taky mi začal semestr, takže zdravím zase z Curychu. Je čas si zase o trochu víc zničit zrak a zkřivit záda. Znamená to ale taky že je čas zase blogovat, a na to se těším. A tak jsem se rozhodl napsat článěk o svém momentálním čtvrtém domově.</p> <h1 id="domov-číslo-čtyři">Domov číslo čtyři</h1> <p>Když člověk studuje v různých městech, tak se i stěhuje. To se nemusí ani do zahraničí, každý student to pozná. Pokud vytáhl paty z domu, tak se musel čas od času někam stěhovat. Skončí kontrakt, zvýší se nájem, najde se lepší příležitost.</p> <p>A tak teď bydlím v novém bytě, a stejně jako ty předchozí je plný mezinárodních lidí. A to se mi moc líbí, protože se s nimi můžu bavit různými jazyky, kterými oni umí mluvit. Když jsem se nastěhoval, tak jsme byli 3: Francesco, Annie a já, fotka je níže.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/funny-glasses-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/funny-glasses-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/funny-glasses-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/funny-glasses.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500" height="300" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Pak se k nám ještě přidala Laura, a už v tom začal být zmatek, jakým jazykem člověk s kým má mluvit. Tak jsem udělal na to hezký grafík, jmenuje se <a href="https://cs.wikipedia.org/wiki/Venn%C5%AFv_diagram">Vénnův diagram</a> a ukazuje nám hodnotu pro každou z 16 možností, podle toho kdo se s kým potká.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/blog/languages-venn-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/blog/languages-venn-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/blog/languages-venn-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/languages-venn.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500" height="300" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Tolik krátká zpráva z nového blogu, já rád uslyším, jestli se dobře používá. Co vám na něm chybí, a co zase přebývá.</p> <p>Mějte se fantasticky, zase znova za týden.</p> <p>Michal</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="weekly-blog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A kde žiju teď? A s kým?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moving to Zurich: A Little Guide to Attacking the Housing Market</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/moving-to-zurich/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moving to Zurich: A Little Guide to Attacking the Housing Market"/><published>2025-05-11T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-11T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/moving-to-zurich</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/moving-to-zurich/"><![CDATA[<p><em>I will try to keep the English version of this blog post up to date if I have new observations.</em></p> <p>I was discussing the other day with a friend of mine how much we miss our social circles from our bachelor studies and high schools. He, coming from Germany and doing his bachelor’s in the UK, had to rebuild his network twice (almost) from scratch. I, coming from a similar experience moving from Czechia to the Netherlands and finally arriving here in Switzerland, agree that it poses many challenges. To describe it, my friend came up with a nice analogy.</p> <p>People are like trees. Wherever we are, we put down roots, and when we move, we get temporarily uprooted. This means that for some time, we will not be doing as well; in particular, we will not be blooming. However, with time, we adjust again. And when the roots are well in the ground again, we can fully consume all the nutrients of the environment and bloom again! Finally, after a period of blooming, some fruits can be gathered…</p> <p>Anyway, now it is May again, the lovely time of knowing your admissions into the next step in your degree and planning your move (read: being stressed and uncertain in your life once again). A couple of people I know have been admitted to ETH, and I was asked a few times to help with housing. I have just moved myself once again, and might move again soon, so I have a lot of pity with the people who have to do the same, so I decided to jot down what is on my mind.</p> <h2 id="budget">Budget</h2> <p>Firstly, let’s discuss the budget you can expect (from what I’ve heard and seen, depending on the size, how many people you share with, and how far you are from the center, of course):</p> <ul> <li>Small rooms in subsidized shared flats: 500-700 CHF</li> <li>Rooms in normal shared flats: 700-1200 CHF</li> <li>Individual studios: 1300-2000 CHF</li> </ul> <p>This is very broad, and you can certainly get lucky and find a much cheaper and better offer (especially if you know someone!). If so, good for you :) But this is what I would expect normally. Personally, I go low budget. I don’t know about you, but I try my best to push down the price to the absolute minimum, even sacrificing comfort for that.</p> <h2 id="where-to-look">Where to look?</h2> <p>I am sure if you googled, you would have found something as well, but here is my personal experience when I was looking for a room for myself:</p> <h3 id="wgzimmer"><a href="https://www.wgzimmer.ch/wgzimmer.html">WGZimmer</a></h3> <p>WG stands for ‘Wohngemeinschaft,’ a shared flat. This is the go-to website where most flats in Zurich post their listings when a room opens up in their flat. Unfortunately, it is maybe too popular, and you have to be quick to get a reply to your message as the people who post expect a lot of replies. However, there are many offers, and I am sure it is a great place to start your search, especially for low budget. I got my second place through here.</p> <h3 id="wohnenethz"><a href="https://www.wohnen.ethz.ch/">wohnen.ethz</a></h3> <p>This is the official website of the universities in Zurich. You can only register if you are a student. There are fewer offers but also fewer people responding, so you might be able to get through more easily. I got my first place through here.</p> <h3 id="flatfox"><a href="https://flatfox.ch/">FlatFox</a></h3> <p>One of the major housing advertising websites for the whole of Switzerland. It targets a broader market: also big flats and houses are offered there. Many offers, but also many respondents. Very tough to get through. I got some offers through there, but the ones from the previous two were better. But it’s certainly good to keep an eye on this website.</p> <h3 id="subsidized-housing">Subsidized Housing</h3> <p>There are two organizations that offer cheap (somehow subsidized?) housing for students. There is <a href="https://woko.ch/">WoKo</a> and <a href="https://juwo.ch/">Juwo</a>. On their websites, there are occasional listings, but places from these shared flats are often offered through WGZimmer or wohnen.ethz. To live here, you need to meet special criteria (be enrolled as a student, be up to a certain age, and have a low enough income).</p> <h2 id="shameless-promo">Shameless Promo</h2> <p>Recently, I have built a tool for employing LLMs for auto-replying to the listings on the above-mentioned websites. You can find it <a href="https://github.com/MichalTesnar/auto-house">here</a>. I would be very happy if it helps anyone. Let me know if you are using it and want me to improve/change something!</p> <p>That’s it. Thanks for reading, and I hope this helps at least a bit!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="guides"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Finding housing on a tight budget is more difficult than it sounds.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The True Difficulty of Language Learning: When Things Are Not The Way They Seem</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/true-difficulty-of-language-learning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The True Difficulty of Language Learning: When Things Are Not The Way They Seem"/><published>2025-04-27T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-04-27T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/true-difficulty-of-language-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/true-difficulty-of-language-learning/"><![CDATA[<p>If you know me even a slight bit, you know I love learning languages. And I love to do it the natural way: by absorbing the language (through listening and reading, but also generally immersing myself into the culture) and producing (saying at least ‘Hello’ to the speakers of the language if I can).</p> <p>I definitely have to acknowledge that my unhinged personality helps with this a little bit: I am way too extroverted and the fact that I enjoy communication is just very useful in practice of producing the language. Either way, I have had an insanely positive feedback whenever I try to speak a language to the native speakers. People usually really admire my effort and want to help me, and that has pushed me even further, and made me love the effort of learning languages. As you can notice, I am very reward-oriented person in this regard.</p> <p>But this blog is not just my personal reflection, it is about languages. No matter the reasons, I spent a lot of time in exposure to different languages. And I would like to describe the real problems of learning a language. If you have learned some language you know the inherent difficulties: you have to remember a lot of words, sometimes you have to learn a new alphabet, you must know how to pronounce sounds that are not naturally available in your language. You also have to train your mind not to use the other languages that you know, which becomes surprisingly difficult if learning languages within the same group (most notably for me Dutch and German).</p> <p>All of these become quickly evident when trying to learn the language in the traditional text-book-spoon-fed-grammar fashion. My personal learning style, however, is to cut to the chase and try to learn the language directly by listening and speaking. I try to achieve fluency as fast as possible: this kind of learning relies highly on using intuition. But there are many more subtle challenges that defy intuition and I would like to comment on those in this blog. Let me explain what I mean.</p> <h2 id="false-friends--casting-between-languages">False Friends &amp; Casting Between Languages</h2> <p>Did you know that the word ‘meeting’ in Russian refers to a public demonstration? I would have never guessed this, and only by asking a Russian coworker in Russian, if he is joining for the ‘meeting’ (for the lack of knowledge of a better word in Russian) has given me the opportunity to learn about this. I am sure that yourself you have come across many situations where guessing just does not really work. I love to speak to Spanish and Italian people: these languages are in some sense so close to English, which allows the native speakers often ‘cast’ the word from their mother tongue to English and expect to get a pass. A nice example is when a Spaniard asks if you could give him an ‘explication’ of how something works (when they are of course referring to explanation). This is one of the inherent difficulties of learning languages, you have to learn to not trust yourself: what may be similar, might be meaning something completely different.</p> <h2 id="expressions-without-translation">Expressions Without Translation</h2> <p>Sometimes you have the expression on the tip of your tongue, you might translate it by Englishifying it, by Spanishifying it or whatever, but sometimes there is just no way to translate! (ChatGPT complains that the correct form is ‘Anglicizing’ and ‘Hispanicizing’, but I chose to ignore this.) The concept can only be described in a different language, but the sense, the meaning of the word, just does not really exist in a different language. My favorite example for this certainly is the Dutch word ‘gezelligheid’. It could most closely be translated as ‘coziness’. It refers to those moments, when you are with people and you just have this good feeling of being together. It can be just two people, family, or a big group, but the feeling that you feel, the situation can only be described as such. Learning about such new concepts is for me one of the most enriching things about language. You literally expand your horizons with new concepts. You – quite literally – learn to see things you have not seen before: thanks to their language Russian speakers see two versions of blue, that are mostly indistinguishable for the rest of us.</p> <h2 id="completely-different-grammatical-constructions">Completely Different Grammatical Constructions</h2> <p>For most us the way we start speaking a language is to word-for-word translate sentences from our main communicational tongue to the new language. This makes sense, you just learn mappings of singleton words, or simple phrases, and you piece a sentence together. I find it very interesting when this approach fails. One of the experiences when it stopped working for me was when I started learning Spanish, as the language expresses the subject is through conjugation of verbs (instead of saying “I love you.” they say “Te quiero” which would be more like “You I-love”).</p> <p>This is quite a major change one has to internalize to speak Spanish, one you have to tackle quite fast at the beginning otherwise the progress forward is slow. Sometimes, however, different constructions are way more sneaky. One that took me personally a long time was the expression of similarity in Dutch. In English, I would say “A is similar to B”, however, the Dutch language usually expresses this using a verb “A lijkt op B”, which would be more like “A resembles B”. The difficulty in learning to say this is not that there are two new words, it is more that expressing the same thing now takes a completely different form, which is complicated to parse into longer sentences.</p> <h2 id="transferring-constructions--idioms">Transferring Constructions &amp; Idioms</h2> <p>The previously mentioned phenomenon becomes quickly apparent when one knows the native tongue of a person and also the new language. Example I would like to give is when I was talking to a friend of mine who grew up in Germany. He said he was taking a course, but ‘it was just not making fun’. In English, one would saying ‘I was not having fun’, but the Germans use the expression ‘Es macht Spass.’ to put the source of the fun instead of ourselves onto the activity. The way of expressing things seems to be very difficult to unlearn in our brain.</p> <p>Another example comes from translating idioms. In international environment it happens often that when trying to be expressive somebody says: “In my language we say…” which makes no sense to anybody else, and then has to be explained. For example, in Czech when somebody pisses you off, you would say that they are ‘drinking your blood’. Saying this in English sounds very creepy though!</p> <p>Lastly there are just expressions with fixed meaning that is not directly literal and has to be learned. I remember the day I understood that the Dutch mean with ‘Weet ik veel.’ (literally ‘I know a lot.’) that they actually do not know what somebody is talking about, or they do not care. This I really could not have guessed from learning the individual words.</p> <h2 id="subtle-pronunciations-differences">Subtle pronunciations Differences</h2> <p>Three years in the Netherlands, the measure of my proficiency has become the time until I was asked ‘So where are you actually from?’ The grammar and idioms were there, but there was still something missing: the pronunciation. I still cannot pronounce the combination of vowels “eu”, as for example in “keuken” which I pronounce the same as “koken”. Which is terribly wrong. Research shows however, that if you were not exposed to some sounds as a child you cannot produce them later on (apparently this is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perceptual_narrowing">perceptual narrowing</a>). Most recently I had my mind blown by a Dutch friend who explained to me that ‘v’ and ‘f’ in Dutch are not pronounced the same. I would have never guessed: for me the way the Dutch pronounce it sound both as ‘f’ from my Czech mother tongue.</p> <h2 id="emphasis-and-intonation">Emphasis and Intonation</h2> <p>Last, but certainly not the least of all phenomena is emphasis. This has struck me when my Spanish friend told me that I speak Spanish like English, and that is not good. That I need to emphasize more. And this makes sense, you would not expect Norwegian and Italian to be spoken in the same way (notably in the second case, you would be more expressive). And example from Dutch for me is the implicit use of sighing ‘he’ as the end of sentences when you expect some reaction, as in ‘Lekker, he?’ (‘Cool, huh?’). This needs to be acquired to achieve proper fluency.</p> <h2 id="conclusion-c3-proficiency">Conclusion: C3 proficiency</h2> <p>This is my short account of issues when trying to achieve fluency in another tongue. It takes a lot more than reading a textbook, one has to really live it. Knowing the language means knowing the people, their expectations and their culture. When this is done properly one feels the language not only rolling off their tongue but also beating in their heart (which can lead to another <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/languagelearningjerk/comments/lj3dj0/language_learning_ruined_my_life/?rdt=61991">set of problems</a> but that is another story). You start to understand why something is funny, because the humour that comes from the language just directly speaks to you.</p> <p>I call this the ‘C3 Level’ (as adapted to Common European Framework of Reference for Languages). It is when your comprehension is so good you have no trouble arguing over the phone, whispering in the lecture, quick gossip in fast-paced emotional conversation or following an exchange in the gym changing rooms (that is the hardest for me, tends to be chaotic, very reaction-based on short sentences, usually held among multiple people). The final step towards glory comes when you also understand puns or word-based jokes: somebody just messes up a part of a word on purpose, and you are on the floor laughing.</p> <p>This is the proficiency us language learners are only dreaming of.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="guides"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When it is not just about word to word translations.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Math do I Need for AI? Catch-Up Guide for RUG AI Undergrads</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/rug-math-guide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Math do I Need for AI? Catch-Up Guide for RUG AI Undergrads"/><published>2025-03-15T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-15T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/rug-math-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/rug-math-guide/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>“So why did you choose Groningen?” A question that I have been asked multiple times after disclosing I study or studied there. The answer was “There is a unique program in AI.” Now, almost a year after finishing the program I am reflecting more and more about what the program gave me. More and more I come to realize how much breadth was explored, learning about philosophy, cognitive psychology, and biology of the brain is not what most CS undergrads can flex with. However, as the field of machine learning is not stopping to grow, I myself as a student of that program had found out that the depth of the knowledge is insufficient to gain a deep understanding of the material at hand, to read papers and maybe even contribute to the research in a meaningful way. I mean, test yourself right now.</p> <h3 id="linear-regression">Linear regression</h3> <p>(Sorry I broke LaTeX, working on fixing it, hopefully you can still orient yourself here.)</p> <p>The simplest model in ML for modeling relations relates targets <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">y</code> (an n-dimensional vector) with design matrix <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">X</code> (an n by d matrix) through vector <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">β</code> (a d-dimensional vector) with some Gaussian noise <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">w</code> added.</p> <p>y = X * β + w</p> <p>We can see that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">β̂ = (X&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; * X)&lt;sup&gt;-1&lt;/sup&gt; * X&lt;sup&gt;T&lt;/sup&gt; * y</code> is an unbiased estimator of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">β</code> using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">E[w] = 0</code>:</p> <p>E[(X<sup>T</sup> * X)<sup>-1</sup> * X<sup>T</sup> * y] = E[(X<sup>T</sup> * X)<sup>-1</sup> * X<sup>T</sup> * (X * β + w)] = (X<sup>T</sup> * X)<sup>-1</sup> * X<sup>T</sup> * X * β = β</p> <p>Finally, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">β̂</code> is also the least-squares estimator, for which we can prove this error bound.</p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>E[</td> <td> </td> <td>β̂ - β</td> <td> </td> <td><sup>2</sup>] = σ<sup>2</sup> * (d / n)</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p><em>Remark:</em> The least squares is a convex function so there is a unique minimum which can be found in polynomial time using gradient descent.</p> <h3 id="wait-what">Wait what?</h3> <p>So, how did reading this feel? No, I am not trying to discourage you here and gatekeep machine learning knowledge from you! This is literally taken from the first chapter of my <a href="https://lecturenotes.cope.ethz.ch/alg4ds/spring25/A001/home.html">master’s course</a>, and except for the last theorem I have not left out any extra explanations.</p> <p>When I was in my second year taking <em>Introduction to Machine Learning</em>, I was not able to read this fluently and make sense out of it. I am putting this mildly, cause I do not want to presume what your level is, maybe you are just fine. But I was genuinely intimidated when I saw the closed form solution for linear regression. God, I had no clue what those weird brackets ($| \cdot |$) really meant, and that double $\mathbb{E}$ somebody told me was an <em>expectation</em>. The expression <em>gradient descent</em> I knew from pictures of colorful loss landscapes but did not know what it really was and <em>polynomial time</em> was not really my biggest friend either.</p> <p>The truth is in ML, as in any other branch, math is just a language we use to describe abstract objects we talk about (If you want to get philosophical I recommend reading <a href="https://www.maths.ed.ac.uk/~v1ranick/papers/wigner.pdf">The unreasonable effectiveness of mathematics in the natural sciences by Wigner</a>).</p> <p>If you want to understand what it is really about you need to get fluent in this language. It takes some time, but it is worth it (my journey is far from done, but I am way further than I was in my first year of BSc AI). To help you on the journey, you can enroll in any of the BSc Mathematics courses. They have great tradition and are (mostly well taught). Here, I establish a list of courses that are relevant, and I try to give a bit of context why (in my humble opinion).</p> <h2 id="essential-tier">Essential Tier</h2> <p>These courses will help you obtain sufficient mathematical dexterity (credits to Andrei Girjoaba for this naming) to read mathematical texts and understand the ideas behind them. For your convenience I have added links to Ocasys, where you can view more information.</p> <p><strong>IMPORTANT DISCLAIMER</strong>: THESE COURSES DO NOT COVER THE SAME STUFF AS THE COURSES IN AI CURRICULUM CALLED ‘FOR AI’. I cannot understate this, you will be challenged way more. Even if you passed ‘Linear Algebra and Multivariable Calculus for AI’ with a 10, you will get challenged in both Linear Algebra and Calculus for Math. This is true especially for Statistics for Math, which covers completely different things than AI Statistics.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA020-05"><strong>Linear Algebra I</strong></a>: Essential for understanding spectral decomposition and the idea of subspaces. This is needed for understanding dimensionality reduction techniques like PCA, which are at the core of machine learning. As a plus, this course is introductory and it teaches proof techniques such as proof by contradiction, which is useful if you haven’t done that in the past.</li> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA035-05"><strong>Linear Algebra II</strong></a>: Essential for understanding singular value decomposition, which is also one of the essential mathematical tools. The latest example of usage is in understanding vanishing and exploding gradients phenomena of RNNs.</li> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA029-05"><strong>Calculus II</strong></a>: Gradient is one of the main topics. This will be your best friend if you ever want to train a neural net. Hand in hand with it goes chain rule. If you do not trust me it is important, try to explain backpropagation without it. (You might want to take <a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA003-05"><strong>Calculus I</strong></a> before if you do not trust yourself too much with your math skills, I have not done it myself and managed, but honestly I still struggle a bit with things like Fourier Series that are treated there)</li> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA046-05"><strong>Probability Theory</strong></a>: Expectation, variance, probability distribution. Trust me, this is a must. The notions are not that difficult once profoundly understood, but this hard course is definitely worth the pain. Highly recommended.</li> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA009-05"><strong>Statistics</strong></a>: ML is just Stats on steroids. Estimators play the main role in this course. The word likelihood finally started making sense to me in this course too. Finally, you also get insight into p-values and confidence intervals. Priceless.</li> <li>(Editor’s Pick) <a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA012-05"><strong>Analysis</strong></a>: Alef Sterk is one of the best lecturers that I have encountered so far, and even though this course does not directly contribute to ML understanding I still recommend it cause it gives you a stronger basis. You get better at proving and in mathematical thinking.</li> </ul> <h2 id="pro-tier">Pro Tier</h2> <p>This is the list of courses ‘I wish I have done’. These are more advanced (=mostly 2nd year math) courses that give you background insight into what is going on in ML. They are not essential, but check them out and if any of the theory seems appealing then certainly go for it. They are all relevant for different areas of ML.</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA024-05"><strong>Probability and Measure</strong></a>: If you want to go more into depth into Probability Theory, this is a course that you want. This gives you the technical background for that (didn’t take this one).</li> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA054-05"><strong>Introduction to Optimization</strong></a>: Keyword <em>gradient descent</em>. Optimization is key for training neural nets. This course goes a wee bit too deep, but the first half is definitely relevant.</li> <li><a href="http://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA033-05"><strong>Functional Analysis</strong></a>: AKA Linear Algebra III, teaches you more about linear operators and functionals. Very good stuff. Also by Alef Sterk.</li> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA031-05"><strong>Dynamical Systems</strong></a>: Recurrent neural networks are modeling dynamical systems, this course will help you appreciate that better (didn’t take this one).</li> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA036-05"><strong>Metric and Topological Spaces</strong></a>: Reinforcement Learning needs this. Without fixed point theorem, how does the fact that Bellman operator is a contraction help you? (Didn’t take this one).</li> <li><a href="https://ocasys.rug.nl/current/catalog/course/WBMA022-05"><strong>Multivariable Analysis</strong></a>: Keyword <em>manifold</em>, these mythical mathematical objects pop up in learning theory from time to time. Maybe it is a stretch, but could also come in handy (didn’t take this one).</li> </ul> <h2 id="closing">Closing</h2> <p>Doing mathematics is like eating vegetables. I am not saying you have to do it, some people do without it and they are doing just fine. But it certainly helps, and I think that if you read into some papers before and after taking the courses that I suggest, you will have a completely different experience with them! (And passing courses like ‘Neural Networks’ will be a breeze.)</p> <p>And no, these courses will neither teach you that you should normalize your input when training a neural net nor explain what torch dataloader is. Anyway, let me know if this was helpful and if you have courses that you would like to add to the list or if you completely disagree with my perspective.</p> <p>And do not forget, if you have any questions the study advisors usually know the best, and they are very helpful, so do not hesitate to talk to them. Personally, they have helped a whole lot during my studies!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="guides"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Compression of knowledge of a recent graduate.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Exam Season at ETH: A Collective Hysteria</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/collective-hysteria/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Exam Season at ETH: A Collective Hysteria"/><published>2025-02-25T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-25T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/collective-hysteria</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2025/collective-hysteria/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="title">Title</h2> <p>Dear readers, I am happy to welcome you back to this blog. I have been waiting a long time to write once again, but I promised myself I would only post after the exams. I have come to think of my writing as a way of managing my mental state. You see, I do not like complaining to others about how sh<em>t my life is because, objectively speaking, it really is *not</em>. I am mostly healthy, mostly able to feed myself, and mostly socially successful as a young person. However, I am still human, and as part of my nature, I get used to how good I am doing and want to strive for more. When more does not come, I get frustrated. But telling somebody just feels unfair because I usually do not think through what I want to say. Writing posts gives me more time to fully assess the situation I am in. As I usually write over multiple days, I have time to reflect on my situation as a whole. More often than not, it helps me realize that things are actually going quite alright. On top of that, it has been really heartwarming to talk to you guys (whoever reads my blog). Apart from a lot of positive feedback, it has many times started conversations in which we cut directly to the topic. I hope to repeat this beautiful cycle, so let me comment on my last set of exams.</p> <h2 id="my-results">My Results</h2> <p>Without digging unnecessarily deeply into the numerical results that I have obtained, I would like to note that I have completed 34 ECTS credit points this semester, which consisted of one 4 ECTS course based on coursework only and 30 ECTS from courses with exams between January 22 and 30. As of now, I have officially received all credits from these courses. Now, let me comment on how these exams have challenged me.</p> <h2 id="exams">Exams</h2> <p>I completed my bachelor’s in the Netherlands, where the semester is split into two parts, each with its own teaching period and exam season. The coursework is based on collaboration and quick feedback cycles. Students also submit a lot of homework, which counts as a major part of the performance assessment (usually ~30-40%).</p> <p>In stark contrast to the Netherlands, at ETH, most of the weight in performance assessment is based on the final exam. For the four courses in which I had an exam, each final exam accounted for 100% of the grade, with the possibility of earning a 5% boost through coursework submitted during the semester. This distribution was very different from what I was used to and took some time to adjust to.</p> <p>Additionally, one cannot select courses based on how exams are scheduled because they are assigned after everyone has enrolled. This is quite annoying since if you are not taking the most common combinations of subjects, the algorithm can assign you all your exams in a very tight schedule. Finally, most exams do not have scheduled reattempts, meaning that a second attempt is usually only possible during next year’s session.</p> <p>Most importantly, however, is the difference in expectations regarding how much you are expected to know. While in the Netherlands, to get full points, you would need perfect knowledge of the subject and flawless execution, here at ETH, you can achieve the best mark even without answering all questions correctly. To pass, you might need to know less than half of the material. The exams are generally designed to be impossible to solve perfectly, and mistakes are expected. The current exam is usually very different from previous years, so whereas in my bachelor’s, I would study to beat the exam, here I am humbled by the material itself. Thankfully, results are graded on a curve, so even after some terrifying experiences, the results were quite satisfying.</p> <h2 id="exam-season">Exam Season</h2> <p>I also want to reflect on the exam period as a whole. ETH reserves a period for studying before the exams, giving students a month with no scheduled classes (and even two months in summer), allowing them to focus solely on revision. This was a challenging time for me, but one I actually look back on fondly. Each day, I would wake up, go to the gym, then head to the library. Later, my classmates and I would grab lunch at Mensa. Then, it was back to the library to study until my brain was fried. Go home, sleep, and repeat. It sounds terrible, but there was something beautiful about it. I found my rhythm and worked through the material at a reasonable pace. I learned to be satisfied without feedback on my performance, simply existing as a happy observer in the realm of knowledge.</p> <p>Here, I have to say thank you to all the people who were there with me along the way. I am very sure I would not have been able to handle it on my own. I think we all struggled a lot, but doing it together made it much easier. At the same time, however, I think we made it harder for each other as well. We were all pretty scared, and we kept telling each other how impossible it is to pass all the challenging courses. As you can guess, in the end it didn’t go so badly. However, as I am (mostly) among first-year master students, we all had little experience with how it goes. We just reinforced the fear in each other, it was a collective hysteria of some sorts. With the first results being announced, we have all calmed down signficantly. I think next exam season will not be easier by any means, but will certainly be a lot more relaxed.</p> <h2 id="ambitions">Ambitions</h2> <p>To be honest, I am very happy I made it through this session alive. As I noted in previous blog posts, I lacked any feedback on whether I was following the curriculum properly, which made things really difficult for me. Right now, I feel very satisfied. My grades are far from perfect, but I am happy with what I got. Moving to Zürich has certainly challenged me enough—no need to be a perfectionist about it. However, that cannot be said for everyone around me.</p> <p>One thing I had not realized before coming here is that about half of my classmates want to pursue a PhD afterward. Hence, they care deeply about their grades, as they are a major part of their application. Moreover, most people here were at the top of their class during their bachelor’s and are not ready to let go of their academic dominance. So, for them, getting a 5/6 is not satisfying but rather a disappointment.</p> <p>Personally, I never thought about a PhD, though the environment I am in is slowly changing my opinion. I went from not considering it at all to suddenly seeing it as a real possibility, though it is certainly not my primary goal.</p> <p>With that being said, just like the Kondi class I attended yesterday (an extreme version of body-pump, typical for Zürich): before I could catch my breath, it was time to go again. Last week, the new semester started, and I already have material to catch up on. With a bit less than 3/4 of the way to go, now is the time to keep up the pace.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How human fear can make a mountain out of a mole hill.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I am Quitting ChatGPT: and Why You Should Too</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2024/quitting-llms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I am Quitting ChatGPT: and Why You Should Too"/><published>2024-12-15T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-15T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2024/quitting-llms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2024/quitting-llms/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Yes, I know it’s a clickbait title, but before you accuse me of being against progress, please read a little to understand what I’m trying to express.</em></p> <p><em>For the purposes of this text, large language models and ChatGPT are used interchangeably.</em></p> <h3 id="just-one-quick-question">Just One Quick Question</h3> <p>Try to answer and then read on.</p> <p><em>What is the population of Poland?</em></p> <p>Unless you are one of the thirty-six million people who live there, you might have a bit of a difficult time answering. Or maybe not. Because you have the internet, and just opening a new tab in whatever browser and typing it out gives you a response within microseconds. However, this means we do not spend time thinking about the answer. This observation certainly has been made before, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2019/oct/03/before-the-internet-broke-my-attention-span-i-read-books-compulsively-now-it-takes-willpower">access to technology shortens our attention spans</a> and <a href="https://www.cmhs-sarasota.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Is-Google-Making-Us-Stupid_Carr.pdf">generally changes the way we interact with information</a>. In fact, I have not even read the articles I linked; I just skimmed them to verify that they fit my narrative.</p> <p>In recent years, humanity has created many powerful tools thanks to which we get quick and robust access to more information. However, this quick gain also causes to lose a skill:</p> <ul> <li> <p>The most obvious example is <em>pocket calculators</em>. Nearly every device nowadays has one implemented in it, so none of us have to make errors when doing mental math. In fact, what used to be an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_(occupation)">occupation of a computer</a> has fully been taken over by the machine, which was very fittingly given the same name.</p> </li> <li> <p>My favorite example is Google Maps. If I am in a new city without a guide (be it friends, family or a tour guide), I have to pay way more attention to where I am myself and end up remembering the topology a lot better. However, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms14652">research shows that using maps in your phone</a> has the same effect as having a guide by your side. Easy access to navigation makes it unnecessary to create a mental representation of the world. You always know whether the next step should be right or left. Funny consequence of this me rotating with my phone in middle of the street to see where the arrow points me. I am not used to looking at how the streets around look like to figure out where to go.</p> </li> <li> <p>Last one is tribute to my mom. She would always make fun of me, that I do not know how the alphabet goes. That is not because I have a disorder, or my mom is mean, but simply because my mom has studied languages at a university during times when online dictionaries were not a thing. Knowing the alphabet intuitively was super useful to speed up lookup in dictionaries. As a result, my mom is fast with answering questions like ‘whether <em>p</em> comes before <em>s</em> in the alphabet’ or not, while I have to recite the whole alphabet to get it right.</p> </li> </ul> <p>Now we looked at some previous tools and what they did to us. But now we have a new tool entering the game…</p> <h3 id="the-almighty">The Almighty</h3> <p>I am sure you tried it out yourself. It is so easy to talk to. You do not even need an account, just type <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">chatgpt.com</code> into your browser and voilà, you can start getting responses. What is more, it is integrated in just about every tool you can use nowadays. It is truly remarkable piece of technology, which condenses real-world knowledge in written form on demand. Some goes as far as to say it reaches the level of graduate students across all subjects. It is ready there for you 24/7 to solve any problem…</p> <p>…and so I use it frequently in my life.</p> <p><em>It is Monday evening. The deadline for my assignment is at midnight. I really cannot get this program to work. ‘Why is this not working?’ I keep asking myself. Finally, I copy paste the code into ChatGPT, asking for help. It points out an error in code. I fix them. Still not working. Another try. Still not. Then I try another model, Gemini from Google. I am going back and forth… Still cannot find the error…</em></p> <p>Sounds familiar? This has become a common experience for me and my peers. Whenever I encounter a difficult problem, be it a mathematical exercise or picking a Christmas gift for people close to me, I turn to ChatGPT. This is especially true for my studies. You see, I study Computer Science and Mathematics: both very much full of symbol-based problems. And ChatGPT happens to be good at those. With a few clicks and no costs, I can unleash the power of 1.8 trillion parameters of thinking to get myself to the answer. This has changed the way I deal with problems in many ways:</p> <ul> <li> <p>I am more lazy to struggle. As discussed above, at the moment I get stuck, I turn to a ChatGPT. I just generate and re-generate till it eventually works. I think it is very human of me to take the path of the least resistance, as my biology leads me to optimize for my current environment.</p> </li> <li> <p>I do not ask for help from people. Since it is so easy to solve problems ‘on my own’ (read ‘with the help of ChatGPT’) I do not expose my stupidity to other people. Not only does this further enhance impostor syndrome, it makes me less social! I think that is a pity, since solving problems together has helped me build many connections in my life.</p> </li> <li> <p>But most importantly… <em>I feel like I do not think anymore</em>. I was always proud to call myself ‘a goal driven person’, however, lately this has become a pitfall. Instead of creating mental representations that would help me answer difficult questions, I just go directly to the result. I take this shortcut using ChatGPT …</p> </li> </ul> <p>…and that is why I decided to quit.</p> <h3 id="the-new-dawn">The New Dawn</h3> <p>In the same way a child cries out for help to their parents, I would call out to help to ChatGPT whenever I had a problem. I had become a toothless child, not being able to handle anything on my own. You see, my main occupation is being a student. I wake up every day to learn. And with the omnipresence of ChatGPT, I was contributing more to training the model behind it, rather than learning new skills for myself. My relationship towards ChatGPT depends on my current experiences and might change rapidly in the upcoming year, but this is how I feel right now.</p> <p>As I discussed before, with every tool we become more powerful, but at the same time we lose a part of our skills. I think that is okay, and there is no need to go against the tide of technology. However, as I tried to describe above, <strong>I feel like we are letting ChatGPT do reasoning for us.</strong></p> <p>And that is not good.</p> <p>If nothing else, we want to keep our ability to reason under all circumstances. In a sense, this is the exact opposite of ‘critical thinking’ that has been so successfully marketed in education in the recent years. This technology is too powerful to be used without a clear sense of purpose behind its use. What I mean by this is acknowledging what the usage of the tool does to us, and changing our usage of it accordingly.</p> <p><em>Are you working on something that does not matter to you?</em> Maybe looking for a typo? Trying to just once use a programming library you have never seen before? In my opinion no problem, prompt ChatGPT until your fingers hurt and do not try to think. It is alright, tomorrow you won’t know what you did anyway.</p> <p><em>But, are you working on something that is important to you?</em> Creating that new revolutionary algorithm, writing up a blog post or maybe studying for a course at university. Maybe talk to ChatGPT, let it explain or suggest ideas, but do not let it generate the final product for you.</p> <p><strong>I strongly believe that taking hold of the reasoning process will pay off down the line.</strong> When you need to advance on the process you have done before, rewrite it, improve or adjust or even explain, you will have a better mental model of the problem. The examples that go for me are becoming better at solving mathematical problems, which only comes through solving problems, or learning to code better, which cannot be learned through just prompting ChatGPT but has to be done through the pain of doing it.</p> <p>For now, I for myself disabled coding copilot when programming, and try to look up answers on other sources, rather than letting them be generated.</p> <p><em>Unless maybe coding and solving Math problems are obsolete skills, the ones worth learning. But then we have a completely different discussion…</em></p> <h5 id="final-remarks">Final Remarks</h5> <p>The last two blogs I have released have brought me immense joy thanks to all the discussions they have sparked among my peers. If you read even a shortest bit, and you have an opinion, please do let me know! Stop me when you see me to chat, or shoot me a message in private. I am curious if you could find yourself in what I wrote, or maybe if you can call me out that I live in my bubble.</p> <p>And Merry Christmas and Happy Holidays!</p> <p><em>Big shout out to my friend Ryan who has inspired me to make this change as well as keep writing blog posts.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Maybe things that help us also can hurt us.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Studying @ETH: The Dopamine Detox</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2024/mid-semester-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Studying @ETH: The Dopamine Detox"/><published>2024-11-17T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-17T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2024/mid-semester-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2024/mid-semester-review/"><![CDATA[<p>Hello everyone,</p> <p>at the beginning of the semester, around a month ago, I wrote down my impressions from transfer to ETH Zurich. Since then, I have gathered more observations about the student life here, so I thought it is time to jot them down once again. I have finally washed off the first impressions (got a bit used to everything being so clean and expensive), so maybe now its time to share my take on what it is really like here.</p> <p>What is more, some of my friends are applying for master admissions for next year (fingers crossed for all of you guys!), so I hope it could maybe also help them to get a more detailed image of the experience. However, nothing is like experiencing it of course, and everybody sees things differently (so I absolutely reserve the right to be wrong and biased). Now without further ado, let’s get down to the business.</p> <h2 id="study-life">Study Life</h2> <p>Now that I have submitted a few assignments and survived a couple of boring lectures (and many interesting ones!), spends some days in the library, I can share my experience with studying here. Cause that is what I came here for, so how is it?</p> <p>It is a huge dopamine detox. Coming from the Netherlands, I was used to the fast pace of a semester half-sliced into blocks, each of which had its own set of exams. The exam session in the Netherlands has already passed, and here we are only slowly moving past a half of the semester, with exams coming up at the end of January, after the Christmas break. That also means, that so far I have no results. No ECTS credits in the system, no passed courses, nothing I could make my parents (and myself) proud of. This is tough for motivation. I have to learn to keep going despite that.</p> <p>What is more, I have not received a single grade yet. All the homework that I am submitting will be graded at the end of term. For some pass/fail assignments I know that I have made it, but apart from that I cannot tell if they were 55% correct or 95% correct. This adds to the previously stated effect of dopamine deprivation.</p> <p>And a little note on exams, I do not even know when I will have them. Even though they are going to happen only in around two months. At the time of writing, the dates have not been announced. This makes it really difficult to plan. With the latest possible date of exams being 14th of February and the start of the Spring semester on the 17th, there is not much breathing space left for us to get any rest. At least ETH guarantees that your exams will not overlap, no matter the courses you chose. I guess they are running some HUGE optimization in the background to figure out how to align the sessions now… :)</p> <p>Okay, all this trouble aside. Most important question, <em>am I learning anything?</em></p> <p>I would say so. I actually came to realize that I enjoy this slower pace of the semester. Although I might say different things in two months, now I feel that although I do not have my dopamine rush, I have more time to dive in into material before the course is over. This gives me more time to appreciate what I am learning. So, yes, I think so. But as noted, I have no way of verifying now without an exam.</p> <p>Also the style of teaching here relies more on self-learning, it is expected that we cover the ground ourselves, as there are no small group tutorials where we could discuss the material with the TAs as there was in Groningen. However, with LLMs being a free service, one can get pretty far with self-studying. Big respect for the generation of my parents, I cannot imagine studying without internet!</p> <h2 id="campus-life">Campus Life</h2> <p>Sadly, as of 2024 it is not possible for the human body to work 24 hours a day. This means that apart from studying, one ends up doing also other things and chatting to people. And that is where the nice parts come in…</p> <p>The Mensa, also known as the canteen in other countries, is the most remarkable place on campus. My favorite is Untere Mensa of UZH where one can get a meal for 6.10 every day. Lately, I have unlocked the power of asking for ‘a big portion, please’, which the cooks for some reason accept as a challenge to fill the plate so much that it is almost impossible to finish. (And I do not complain.) What is more, getting lunch is a great social activity, during which many people take 40 minutes to an hour to catch up with their peers. Absolute highlights of the week for me!</p> <p>Bars in the city of course have Swiss prices, which is something I might allow myself to experience in the far far future. However, after studying is done, one can head to student bar bQm, located conveniently right at the terrace of ETH to continue the conversations from lunch at Mensa. Overall a very welcoming atmosphere. Complements the hard studying culture at ETH pretty well.</p> <p>In comparison with the Netherlands transportation is not that easy. Many people live quite far from the campus, which incurs long travelling times (30-40 minutes for most people). I used to commute like this during my high school too, but in the Netherlands I just stopped being used to it. Also public transport is less frequent at the end of the day. A consequence of this is that people leave earlier for home, but maybe it is also the fact that we are all a few years older now and value sleep a bit more.</p> <h2 id="personal-life">Personal Life</h2> <p>Apart of studying, we are all people. Since being outside of Czechia, I haven’t stopped enjoying hearing stories of people with international backgrounds. As many Master’s have now a bachelor behind their back, some even including an exchange, anyone I talk to has a great story to share.</p> <p>What is more, we are slowly moving to the age of having serious relationships. Around a week or two ago, it was ‘visiting time’ for many of us. Many of my friends (me included) had their significant ones visit them here in Zürich.</p> <p>For me it has been an opportunity to break away from the daily hustle and do something different, take a few strolls around the city and recall random bits of the history of the city that I remember. More importantly, however, I took a bit of time to slow down and relax. That week I have slept like a baby, and my levels of stress (according to my watch) were at all time low. Even though the backlog has piled up massively, I am happy to have taken the time to spend that time with her. Writing about this now it makes me realize how much I miss her every day :(</p> <p>Let’s turn the page, when it comes to social life, I can also happily announce I have got to know a couple of people at the uni here. This has the nice effect of giving many hugs/handshakes/high-fives/fist-bombs to people on the corridors of our department building. It is something that I was really missing, and it took some time to build. But it is back, and I am loving it. That small ‘hi’ and a smile during a break can really make a difference.</p> <h2 id="mental-life">Mental Life</h2> <p>I have to admit I had quite a rough time these last few months, moving to a new place and figuring out everything. I sometimes have a feeling like if you follow some people studying on social media, that they make it seem like plain sailing. Just enough coffee and you will pull through. But I want to be vocal about the fact that I do not find it easy. Moving to a new country, establishing a new network of friends, getting lost in a new city. It has its challenges.</p> <p>Recently I have been doing better, but I have certainly went through a lot of doubt and personal crises. Yesterday, I have just randomly watched an interview of <a href="https://x.com/jordanbpeterson/status/1815427698703090085?lang=en">Elon Musk done by Jordan Peterson</a>, where he talks about his life crises. Not that I admire Elon (I find him stupid and genius at the same time), but now I am trying to gaslight myself into thinking that having doubts is a sign of greatness. It is all about transforming the doubts into motivation, so produce something meaningful (?).</p> <p>With that being said, I am super grateful if you had time to checkout this post. Let me know if you agree, or disagree, or you do not care. And I wish we get to chat about this soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When studying is not as much fun as it used to be...]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How I Misunderstood Academia: Realizations from Transfer to ETH Zurich</title><link href="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2024/eth-review/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How I Misunderstood Academia: Realizations from Transfer to ETH Zurich"/><published>2024-09-23T14:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-23T14:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2024/eth-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://michaltesnar.github.io/blog/2024/eth-review/"><![CDATA[<p>They say seeing things from a distance gives you a great perspective, and I feel it is really true. Recently, I started my master’s degree in Data Science at the Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich, to the general public known as the ETH. (I was specific in the naming, as the term ETH is misleading: all federal technological institutes in Switzerland are ETH, for example, the EPFL in Laussane is also an ETH, so the ETH Zurich should be referred to as ETHZ). Leaving all the pedantic details aside, I would like to share my first impressions from this institution with the general public. I feel a strong obligation to do so, as the technical university in Zurich is getting more and more popular, many of my peers consider it as their future destination. It is really attractive due to its low tuition and high international recognition. Last year I spent countless hours reviewing curricula of different programs across the world and the admission conditions to select the optimal degree, and I am sure there are many people doing the same this Fall, so hopefully this information can come in handy.</p> <p>And as I have just finished my Bachelor’s degree in the Netherlands, I feel I can give an interesting perspective. Especially, because I have just moved, and I still feel the contrast strongly. At the same time, I have been here just a week, so it is necessary to take all of these conclusions as preliminary.</p> <h2 id="most-things-are-the-same">Most Things Are The Same</h2> <p>…or the changes are just minor. Although it might surprise you a bit that the lectures start 15 minutes past the full hour, and the buildings have floors numbered from E (Erdgeschoss, meaning ground floor) with increasing alphabetical order going up. One gets used to quickly to these small things. They are vital for the survival of a new student, but by no means necessary to discuss.</p> <p>Sometimes I even find myself naming things in the old way, calling the sport association ACLO (as it was named in Groningen) as opposed to ASVZ, which is its true name. That is just because everything works almost in the same way. In the end, they are western European universities. They all have two semesters (somewhat) and a rector up top the organization.</p> <h2 id="menzas-are-awesome">Menzas are awesome!</h2> <p>One thing that is just remarkably better in Zurich, and that is the food for students. In Groningen, all canteens were commercial and not subsidized, a meal on the campus would cost you around 8-15 euros. However, that is just a normal commercial price you would pay for a small meal in the vicinity of the center in some fast food corner. In Zurich, the prices for commercial services are through the roof, however, on university campuses they are curbed by a state subsidy. This means, that a meal that in the centre would cost you 25-30 CHF costs you a half in the school canteen, with the mass production pushing the price down to 7-10 CHF a meal. On top of that, you get the meal instantly, without much waiting (apart from the queue that appears in peak hours).</p> <h2 id="superiority-complex">Superiority Complex</h2> <p>Let’s face it. ETH is proud to be ETH. In the introductory lecture, we have already been congratulated to our admission and told that ‘many would give a lot to even be able to be in our spot’. This was quickly followed by the wishes of good luck of surviving at this institution, as the workload is known to be demanding. ETH harvests a lot of talent from Europe, and is trying to make the best use of it. That means pushing it to the top of its performance. Peer pressure and impostor syndrome are more common than the flu on campus, and one can sense in the air.</p> <p>Funny byproduct of this is that the local student sports association ASVZ has created napping rooms in the school buildings: too tired? Just drop in for a nap! On the faculty social media channel for computing science students, a daily announcement to keep up the motivation is posted. This nicely conveys that some people get really juiced out over the year. Even the teacher on the first day told us that we should take care of ourselves: first eat and sleep, then study. One has to ask themselves what this school is all about if such measures are needed?</p> <p>To say the least, people are proud to be members of this institution. Sometimes even too proud and they let others know. Maybe superiority complex is a bit to strong of an expression, but it is certainly a different feeling from what I am used to from Brno and Groningen.</p> <h2 id="there-is-no-student-life">There is NO Student Life</h2> <p>In very stark contrast with the Netherlands, there is a lot fewer student associations. But that would come as no surprise given that the workload here is so high. However, it becomes even stranger, when asking current students you get quite depressing answers:</p> <ul> <li>So what are your hobbies? <ul> <li>I have none, I study.</li> </ul> </li> <li>Where do you hang out in free time? <ul> <li>(Laughs.) Man, I barely do that anymore.</li> </ul> </li> <li>What is your favorite thing to do in Zurich? <ul> <li>Oh, whenever I can I am out of here. People seem not to have (generally) many other hobbies. They come here to study. That is the mindset here. Very different from the Netherlands, where every motivated student has some side hustle or at least a hobby. <h2 id="ratios">Ratios</h2> <p>The male/female ratio at ETH is clearly messed up, the university reports 2 male to 1 female, but roaming around the campus it feels more like 5:1. One more reason to maintain my relationship I established during my bachelors, since if I were to try to find someone in the university here, I would have a problem. Thankfully, next door is the liberal sciences university of Zurich, where females are plenty.</p> </li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>Another messed up ratio is the one of students to staff. Just two days ago I had a friend complaining to me that he is waiting to be admitted to a course which has a cap of 900 students: all spots were already taken. Graphs show that hiring has generally not kept up with the increasing popularity of ETH in the recent years. It is really hard to get to work with a professor for supervision, way harder than at smaller universities. I was lucky to be supervised in my bachelor’s thesis by an assistant professor, I can just dream of that at ETH.</p> <h2 id="huge-startup-culture">Huge Startup Culture</h2> <p>Now let’s talk a bit professionally. Zurich is not only the banking centre of Switzerland, but there is a lot more business going on around it. And one part ETH is really proud of: the start-ups.</p> <p>Starting from the small to the big, the university has its own Student Project House, where students can prototype their own projects. It hosts a course on entrepreneurship, with counseling and networking events. It even finances a lot of start-ups itself, or helps them get referral for funding. The so-called spin-offs, startups that come from ETH research are a mark of success, bringing billions of CHF in investments every year. This is one of the reasons I have picked Zurich, so this makes me very happy.</p> <h2 id="focus-on-research">Focus on Research</h2> <p>ETH is a research institution, new knowledge is what they crave and need. That is why there is big emphasis on students doing research project with their supervisors (though mainly PhDs or postdocs). There is also a big amount of researches visiting this institution. There are talks, lecture series or symposia almost everyday, and conferences take place here all the time.</p> <h2 id="professors-are-cracked">Professors are Cracked</h2> <p>…and are students too. No genuinely. The Swiss government has the money to pay the best professors, and you can feel it. Profs here have each thousands of citations on their names, and many have founded a company, or achieved something else even more remarkable. The people are the biggest asset of this institution.</p> <h2 id="academia-is-not-made-for-teaching">Academia is NOT Made for Teaching</h2> <p>You might be thinking, Michal, where comes the point you will understand academia? Well, here it is. My recent discovery is that…</p> <p><em>Academia is <strong>not</strong> made for teaching.</em> It is a research institution. It is not a teaching institution. Most staff join it to develop ideas, and rarely to develop talent of others. Teaching is just a by-product of that. Let me give you an analogy.</p> <p>Academia teaching is like your mom cooking. The goal of your mum is to raise you, not to make 5 star meals. She needs to quench your hunger, so she makes food. She manages quite well, and you also learn to like it with time. Academia is the same, it wants researchers and money, so it has to teach. But it does it to the extent that it is good.</p> <p>This realization made me stop assessing university on the quality of its teaching, but more on the quality of its research. Although most of general public join a university to obtain a degree, for the ones on the top we won’t mean more than a side hustle.</p> <p>Thank you for reading so far, I hope you like this post, and I am looking forward to discussing what I wrote here with any of you!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinions"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Is academia there to teach or to compete?]]></summary></entry></feed>